<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo on Wobbly Earth</title>
    <link>http://wobbly.earth/tags/hugo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hugo on Wobbly Earth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 16:50:04 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://wobbly.earth/tags/hugo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>welcome</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 16:50:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On the more material side, you may consider structuring your presentation using narratives, making use of effective graphics and trying to eliminate those parts from your presentation which do not contribute to it. Just that someone at Microsoft thought it was a cool idea to offer transition effects like slides disintegrating in blocks and stars, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it was a good idea. Most people, including me, are not entertained by it but respond allergically to such slide transitions, resulting in an instant distraction from what you&amp;rsquo;re telling. You may also consider avoiding some fonts, which have the potential to cause political uproar. For some, seeing comicsans in your scientific presentation is like saying you like Obamacare in a GOPdebate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, the single piece of advice for making a good presentation is the old boyscout credo: &amp;ldquo;prepared&amp;rdquo;. Once you prepared your presentation, you may want to check if it is effective and can be finished within the allocated time slot. Weathered speakers may know this from their experience, but even better is to rehearse your talk in front of group of friendly but critical peers. For a conference talk, the group would ideally consists of scientists from varying research fields, such that the audience better resembles reality. By rehearsing you (1) know whether your talk fits in the 12 minute limit, (2) can check if your main points came accross, and (3) see if your presentation material looks the way it is supposed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EGU 2016 short course 54 Presentation feedback round, builds on the observation that doing a rehearsal is a very effective way of improving the quality of your talk, whilst building your confidence on the podium. Last year, we organized the short course for the first time, and the feedback encouraged us to organize this again. Bernd Uebbing, early career scientist and participant of last year&amp;rsquo;s round commented: Very helpful general information on how to present scientific results in an interesting way combined with constructive individual feedback after my trial presentation; would recommend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short course is set up as follows. After kicking off with an entertaining talk on presenting, registered participants will give their presentation after which there is time to receive feedback from the organizers and audience. In contrast to your actual conference talk, more time is scheduled for feedback and topics related to presentation skills will be given plenty of attention. Everybody is welcome to attend the short course, but we specifically invite scientists, notably early career scientists, to sign up for a try-out of their EGU talk (PICO or oral).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even after attending our shortcourse, and being very well prepared, you&amp;rsquo;re climbing that podium and are still nervous. But now, you got what it takes to deliver a conference highlight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>