<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wobbly Earth</title>
    <link>http://wobbly.earth/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Wobbly Earth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://wobbly.earth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Consistent Ocean Mass Time Series from LEO Potential Field Missions (CONTIM)</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/project/contim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/project/contim/</guid>
      <description>The DFG funded project CONTIM (Consistent Ocean Mass Time Series from LEO Potential Field Missions), is part of the Priority Program Dynamic Earth, and started in 2015 (initially for 3 years). It&amp;rsquo;s primary goal is to estimate and study ocean mass variations using numerical ocean modelling, precise orbit determination of low earth orbiters (LEO&amp;rsquo;s), and data combination approaches. The project is expected to yield results which are highly relevant for closing the sea level budget, indirectly providing constraints on the ocean warming and the related energy budget of the Earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mind the GRACE Gap, use Swarm</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/mindthegap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/mindthegap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Around Christmas time last year, a falling star, caused by the reentry of the GRACE-2 satellite vehicle, marked the end of an unprecedented gravity mission. It therefore makes sense to find alternatives for the Gravity Recovery and Climate Experiment (GRACE), which can be used to bridge the gap with the GRACE Follow-on mission. A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.solid-earth-discuss.net/se-2017-127/&#34;&gt;recent paper by Christina Lück et al.&lt;/a&gt; now shows whether the Swarm mission can help out in filling this gap.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists! Encrypt your mail if you got nothing to hide</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/gpg_withpforparanoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 20:51:17 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/gpg_withpforparanoid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Up to now, I never bothered to encrypt my email as my attitude was that, as a scientist, I got nothing to hide. But in light of the recently installed science-deprived administration in the US, I&amp;rsquo;m starting to think that a healthy streak of paranoia wouldn&amp;rsquo;t harm after all.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guess what: Sea level does rise when you melt floating ice</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 01:36:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One may suspect that melting of floating ice would not cause a sea level change, but dissolving a chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf may actually change &lt;em&gt;regional&lt;/em&gt; sea level by up to a meter. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/publications/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your academic homepage: outreach booster or narcissistic outlet?</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-you-really-need-an-academic-homepage&#34;&gt;Do you really need an academic homepage?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the abundance of academic homepages and blogs around, I&amp;rsquo;m certainly not the only one who asked himself that question. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the idea of making one myself for a quite a while now, and finally decided to give it a shot. You&amp;rsquo;re currently looking at the result. For those of you interested in the technical details or the idea behind the domain name, there are posts in the making on that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BanD-AID</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/project/bandaid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/project/bandaid/</guid>
      <description>Bringing together several research disciplines to study the Bangladesh delta The Bangladesh delta is home to over 150 million people and located at the confluence of the Ganges, Brahmaputra and Meghna Rivers. The high population density and flat topography make the delta vulnerable to sea level rise, and storm surges. For example, Cyclone Sidr in 2007 caused over 3400 deaths and an economic loss of about US$ 1.7 billion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Profile</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/about/</guid>
      <description>Research Focus I&amp;rsquo;m working as a post-doc researcher at the Institute for Geodesy and Geoinformation at the university of Bonn in Germany. Besides teaching and EGU activities, I use space geodesy to study terrestrial hydrology, oceanographic signals and ice sheet changes. I&amp;rsquo;ve (and am) working a lot with the Gravity Recovery and Climate Experiment to study time variable gravity changes. Furthermore, using radar altimetry over the ocean to study sea level changes is another focus.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>