<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wobbly Earth</title>
    <link>http://wobbly.earth/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Wobbly Earth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 01:36:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://wobbly.earth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Guess what: Sea level does rise when you melt floating ice</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 01:36:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One may suspect that melting of floating ice would not cause a sea level change, but dissolving a chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf may actually change &lt;em&gt;regional&lt;/em&gt; sea level by up to a meter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post was actually inspired by an email I received last week:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subject: Remember Arquimedes before being silly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Roelof,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melting of the Artic ice sheets contributes ZERO to the sea level rise, simply because they are afloat, its basic hydrostatic!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic mistake and a shame to see these words coming from the mouth of a TUDelft graduate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XXXXXXXX,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naval Architect&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I decided to ignore the email because of its tone, and obvious &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man&#34;&gt;strawman argument&lt;/a&gt;. But, since &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skepticalscience.com/Sea-level-rise-due-to-floating-ice.html&#34;&gt;the Archimedes argument has an interesting twist to it&lt;/a&gt; when ice melts in sea water, it was actually a good incentive to write a post on it. Furthermore, there are obviously still people today, who willfully or unwillfully, ignore the melting of grounded ice masses, while misinterpreting &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archimedes%27_principle&#34;&gt;Archimedes&amp;rsquo; principle&lt;/a&gt; in terms of volume instead of mass. So, I guess it doesn&amp;rsquo;t harm to reopen this case and use the dangling chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;misinterpreting-archimedes-principle&#34;&gt;Misinterpreting Archimedes&amp;rsquo; Principle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having Archimedes in mind, one is inclined to reason that, when floating ice melts, the volume of sea water which it displaces will be perfectly compensated by the added volume from the melted ice. If this would be the case, then no net sea level will result from melting floating ice. However, Archimedes&amp;rsquo; principle itself is formulated in terms of forces which are linked to weight (or equivalently mass) and not to volume:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any object, wholly or partially immersed in a fluid, is buoyed up by a force equal to the weight of the fluid displaced by the object&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will see that, in the case of melting ice in sea water, it certainly is not a correct to assume a constant density throughout the melting process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;grounded-versus-floating-ice&#34;&gt;Grounded versus Floating Ice&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/Grounding-line.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A large part of the world&amp;#39;s ice sheets are resting on the bedrock, compared to floating ice which either comes from the calving of glaciers or is formed at the surface during cold winter times.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antarcticglaciers.org/glaciers-and-climate/ice-ocean-interactions/grounding-lines/&#34;&gt; 
            Source: antarcticglaciers.org
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To get an idea of all the factors at play here, one has to distinguish between ice which rests on the bedrock and ice which is afloat. The other issue, as discussed in this post, is that floating ice may induce regional changes in sea level when melted. I addressed these issues in the email reply, which I repeat here for completeness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear XXXXXXX,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;seeing that you took the effort to write me an email, and noticing that the topic obviously got you emotionally involved, I took the liberty to write you a quick response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to set the record straight, you can not have heard me claiming that floating sea ice is driving  sea level change, so I don&amp;rsquo;t understand where you got that idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, grounded (not floating) glaciers and ice sheets do contribute to sea level change. Besides the obvious Greenland ice sheet, the Arctic houses several islands which are home to grounded glaciers (e.g. Nova Zembla, Svalbard. etc), you only need to have a look at google earth to spot a few of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, and here&amp;rsquo;s some food for thought, melting sea-ice may actually cause (small) changes in sea level.  The salt concentration in ice bergs and sea -ice is less  than that of the sea water which holds it buoyant. So if sea-ice melts in the water , the local salt concentration, and hence the sea water density, decreases. To maintain a constant pressure at the bottom of the ocean, which is a fine assumption when considering the surrounding waters to be unchanged,  one would (regionally) need a higher column of less dense water. The Archimedes argument breaks down there because the density of the water obviously does not remain constant throughout the melting process.  Density changes also occur when the temperature of the sea water changes due to the latent heat needed to convert ice to water, essentially counteracting (some of) the above effect. So regionally, melting of icebergs and sea-ice could in fact cause some sea level change. However, this effect is expected to be smaller than the direct contributions of the grounded ice sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You being a naval architect and former university employee, I trust you to be skeptical enough to reconsider your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kind regards,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roelof Rietbroek&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. In the future, please refrain from using patronizing language such as &amp;ldquo;Remember Arquimedes before being silly&amp;rdquo;, it does not impress me and it degrades an open discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retropect, I apologize for the final sneer, a little patronizing by itself, but considering how the correspondence started of, it could have been worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I won&amp;rsquo;t go into detail on these grounded ice sheets, but these are indeed significant contributors to global sea level rise. It is the floating ice, which either has been calved of a glacier (i.e. ice bergs),  or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lAupJzH31tc&#34;&gt;sea ice which may form at the ocean&amp;rsquo;s surface under wintery conditions&lt;/a&gt;, which will be in focus here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;melting-a-piece-of-the-larsen-c-ice-shelf&#34;&gt;Melting a piece of the Larsen C ice shelf&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time now, scientist have been looking at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projectmidas.org/blog/a-growing-rift-in-larsen-c/&#34;&gt;a growing crack in the Larsen C ice shelf&lt;/a&gt;. The part which could potentially break off covers about 6000 km^2, which is about 1/7th of the Netherlands (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.volkskrant.nl/wetenschap/gigantische-ijsvlakte-antarctica-staat-op-breken~a3851188/&#34;&gt;the area of North and South Holland together&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/larsenCchunk.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A crack growing in the Larsen C ice sheet may lead to a significant piece breaking off&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projectmidas.org/blog/a-growing-rift-in-larsen-c&#34;&gt; 
            Source: Project MIDAS
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Using this as an extreme example, one could try to compute the sea surface height change after melting this chunk in a region of the ocean. In order to quantify this in a reasonable amount of time, we would need to make some design choices and simplifications. I implemented these in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/strawpants/IceshelfMeltDemo&#34;&gt;some matlab scripts&lt;/a&gt; which everyone interested can download and tinker with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;1-define-the-chunk-of-ice&#34;&gt;1 Define the Chunk of Ice&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on some educated guesses the following chunk of the Larsen C shelf is to be melted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surface area: 6000 sq. km&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ice Thickness: 200 m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ice density: 917 kg per cubic m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;2-define-the-pool-of-sea-water-to-melt-the-ice-in&#34;&gt;2 Define the pool of sea water to melt the ice in&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the pool of water must be large enough to facilitate the melting of the ice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surface area: 3 times the area of the ice shelf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depth of the affected water: 2000 m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial in situ temperature: (allowed to vary from -2 to 22 deg. Celcius)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial salt concentration: 34.5 &lt;a href=&#34;http://salinometry.com/pss-78/&#34;&gt;practical salinity units&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mean density of seawater: 1027 kg per cubic m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;3-make-a-monster-slush-puppy-from-the-larsen-c-chunk&#34;&gt;3  Make a monster slush Puppy from the Larsen C chunk&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I mean by this is that we conceptually disintegrate the ice shelf and distribute the ice evenly without melting. This step is needed as we want to let the melting affect the sea water evenly over the entire pool of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;4-compute-the-new-temperature-and-salinity-of-the-sea-water-after-melting&#34;&gt;4 Compute the new temperature and salinity of the sea water after melting&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea water and ice are really awkard substances, and respond non-linearly to temperature and salinity changes. To maintain thermodynamic consistency (i.e. conserve energy), I used software from the empirically determined &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.teos-10.org&#34;&gt;Thermodynamic Equation Of Seawater (TEOS)&lt;/a&gt; to compute the sea water response (i.e. new temperature and salinity) to melting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;5-integrate-the-density-changes-over-the-affected-column-to-compute-sea-surface-height-change&#34;&gt;5 Integrate the density changes over the affected column to compute sea surface height change&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the TEOS software again, we can now compute the density from the temperature and salinity profile before and after the melt event. These can than be numericaly intergrated over the entire water column to compute the sea surface height change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melting-the-larsen-c-chunk-of-ice-may-yield-over-1-meter-of-regional-sea-level&#34;&gt;Melting the Larsen C chunk of ice  may yield over 1 meter of regional sea level&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the result surprised me as well. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting sea level changes over a meter. But then again, it is a gigantic piece of ice which has been melted here in a &amp;lsquo;relatively&amp;rsquo; small area. The interesting thing is that the sea surface height change strongly depends on the initial temperature of the sea water. The plot below shows the dependency on the initial temperature of the sea water. And there are some interesting observations which can be made.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/LarsenCSealevel.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Regional sea level change (blue dashed line) when a 6000 sqkm floating chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf would be melted in a pool of sea water which is about 33 times the mass of the ice shelf itself. The blue area indicates the range of initial temperatures which didn&amp;#39;t allow a complete melting of the ice. The green line indicates the drop in temperature of the sea water.&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Melting ice in colder waters cause a larger sea level rise. The maximum sea surface change (130 cm) occurs close to the point where the melting brings the sea water closest to its freezing temperature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you would tug the ice shelf to tropical waters (&amp;gt; 18 deg. C), the melting would actually cause a sea level drop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The temperature drop of the sea water increases when starting of with warmer waters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, although floating ice is not expected to directly contribute much to global mean sea level rise, it&amp;rsquo;s contribution to regional sea level may be large enough to be detectable with sea surface height measurements such as those from for example radar altimetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that, even for global mean sea level rise, the volumetric changes due to melting of ice shelfs do cause a small net sea level rise. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2010GL042496/full&#34;&gt;Shepherd et al. 2010&lt;/a&gt; found a net contribution of  49 ± 8 microns per year, which is small compared to the currently observed global mean sea level rate of about 3 mm/yr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above experiment comes with it&amp;rsquo;s assumptions (e.g. no circulation and energy exchange with the surrounding waters), but can nevertheless be used as a conceptual model. Readers who find errors in the code are of course encouraged to report this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/publications/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your academic homepage: outreach booster or narcissistic outlet?</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-you-really-need-an-academic-homepage&#34;&gt;Do you really need an academic homepage?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the abundance of academic homepages and blogs around, I&amp;rsquo;m certainly not the only one who asked himself that question. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the idea of making one myself for a quite a while now, and finally decided to give it a shot. You&amp;rsquo;re currently looking at the result. For those of you interested in the technical details or the idea behind the domain name, there are posts in the making on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best response I got when discussing the starting of blog with friends was probably in the line of &amp;ldquo;Good on you!: but don&amp;rsquo;t you think a homepage is a tad archaic?&amp;ldquo;. Well &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.igg.uni-bonn.de/apmg/index.php?id=rietbroek&#34;&gt;my institutional homepage&lt;/a&gt; sure has a pretty archaic look, and, frustatingly, I can&amp;rsquo;t change that. Interestingly, that&amp;rsquo;s also my prime reason to venture into this: &amp;ldquo;having the freedom to design and style your own public appearance, and being able to better manage your own outreach efforts. Of course one could try to reach out using a facebook profile, but frankly speaking, I don&amp;rsquo;t want facebook to take control over my homepage, and bombard you with irrelevant information (i.e. adds), although I&amp;rsquo;ll certainly use it to share links to reach a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #f0f0f0&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #007020; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; ( Outreach &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; Publications )
{
    &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;Publications;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the current academic situation, outreach efforts are still underappreciated compared to publishing papers, so the incentive clearly lies at publishing more papers instead of building a blog. Most of the research grants I&amp;rsquo;ve seen put the weight (=resources) on researching and publishing in respectable journals, compared to outreach activities (if specified at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that people don&amp;rsquo;t want researchers to reach out to the general public. Recently, Sander Dekker, dutch secretary of the ministery of education, culture and research, plead that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scienceguide.nl/201609/de-echte-waarde-van-wetenschap.aspx&#34;&gt;researchers have the moral duty to communicate their findings to the general public&lt;/a&gt;, but sadly failed to acknowledge that researchers are expected to do this voluntarily in their own (precious) time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have the feeling though that there is a paradigm shift going on. For example, Rolf Hut voiced this in stating that &lt;a href=&#34;http://rolfhut.nl/2016/07/27/why-scientists-should-write-blogs-instead-of-articles/&#34;&gt;scientists should write blogs instead of articles&lt;/a&gt;. I sure won&amp;rsquo;t refrain from writing papers, but it is food for thought, and one&amp;rsquo;s results surely would reach a broader audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also other signs that outreach efforts are getting more important. I personally really like the outreach efforts of the EU funded &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.egsiem.eu&#34;&gt;EGSIEM project&lt;/a&gt;. The website offers regular blogposts on the project&amp;rsquo;s activities, where I should mention that it is a remarkable achievement to gather so many blogposts from fellow scientists, who are busy writing papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Germany, the science funding body &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dfg.de&#34;&gt;DFG&lt;/a&gt; is putting effort in setting an example. Since january 2016, they have their own &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dfg_public&#34;&gt;twitter account&lt;/a&gt; (woop woop!). And since june 2016, they started making &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dfg.de/klimataucher&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; of climate related research targeted at a broader german public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-if-your-homepage-turns-into-a-narcissistic-outlet&#34;&gt;What if your homepage turns into a narcissistic outlet?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely, I hope that the occasional visitor of this website is entertained and informed, instead of being bored by a polished profile of an apparent &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.nl/citations?user=qGuYgMsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;academic research superstar&lt;/a&gt;. That being said, I do intend to show a bit of myself, and to highlight my own research work. And sharing such things should be an enjoyable activity, otherwise it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to start a blog in the first place. Furthermore, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t the researcher himself be the ideal person to disseminate his research to wider public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;double-barrel-science-communication&#34;&gt;Double barrel science communication&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However some may argue that researchers have the tendency to stay too technical (read: boring) when communicating science, and that this task should better be left to journalists. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/life-and-physics/2016/apr/16/justin-trudeau-and-quantum-computers&#34;&gt;Although some journalists think it&amp;rsquo;s even better to have politicians explain the science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/rRmv4uD2RQ4?&#34; 
  style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with journalistic stories is that they often filter out a fair share of relevant science while shaping the story around dramatic headlines. Honestly, you can&amp;rsquo;t really blame the journalists for doing this, as they &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-wales-34213693&#34;&gt;crucially depend on clicks&lt;/a&gt;, but it may deform the results of the actual study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who said that you have to choose? Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s better to go for a double barrel approach and use both the professional media and a direct piece by the scientist. In such situations, if you have your academic homepage up and running, don&amp;rsquo;t you think it is an ideal place to add those extra bits of science?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BanD-AID</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/project/bandaid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/project/bandaid/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bringing-together-several-research-disciplines-to-study-the-bangladesh-delta&#34;&gt;Bringing together several research disciplines to study the Bangladesh delta&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bangladesh delta is home to over 150 million people and located at the confluence of the Ganges, Brahmaputra and Meghna Rivers. The high population density and flat topography make the delta vulnerable to sea level rise, and storm surges. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://reliefweb.int/report/bangladesh/cyclone-sidr-bangladesh-damage-loss-and-needs-assessment-disaster-recovery-and&#34;&gt;Cyclone Sidr in 2007 caused over 3400 deaths and an economic loss of about US$ 1.7 billion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to cyclones, several other factors play a role in Bangladesh. Monsoonal flooding, salt water intrusion, coastal and river bank erosion, and drink water contamination , all affect the livelihoods of the people in Bangladesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collaborative research project &lt;em&gt;Bangladesh Delta: Assessment of the Causes of Sea-level Rise Hazards and Integrated Development of Predictive Modeling Towards Mitigation and Adaptation&lt;/em&gt; (BanD-AID) was initiated in 2012, and funded through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://belmontforum.org&#34;&gt;Belmont Forum&lt;/a&gt; for a 3 year period (funding ends in 2016). It brought together researchers from various disciplines ranging from geodesy to social sciences from the US, Germany, France, Bangladesh and Australia, in an effort to assess sea level change and its implications in the region. The research involved the use of satellite data, installing geodetic receivers and tide gauges, as well the undertaking of questionaires in selected villages.

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/TGbandaid.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The bridge was the most stable point available to mount a tide gauge equipped with a GPS-receiver&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://geodesy.geology.ohio-state.edu/Belmont-Band-AID/Events.html&#34;&gt; 
            Source: http://belmont-sealevel.org
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this project, the contributions of our working group in Bonn (J. Kusche, B. Uebbing and R. Rietbroek) have covered the use of satellite observations and tide gauges (pdfs of related publications can be downloaded found &lt;a href=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/data/Kusche2015_finalMS.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/data/PNAS-2016-Rietbroek-1519132113+SI.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. For example, we compared a combination of spaceborne radar measurements and time variable gravity fields from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://grace.jpl.nasa.gov/mission/grace/&#34;&gt;GRACE&lt;/a&gt; mission)) with sea level variations at several tide gauges. Fig. 2 illustrates the finding that sea level variations originate mainly from the coastal regions.

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/BayofBengalcorr.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fig. 2 Sea level variations measured at tide gauges reflect variations along large stretches of the coastal ocean. The figures depict the correlation of the tide gauge data with sea level variations from a combination of radar altimetry and GRACE gravity observations.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2015JC011471&#34;&gt; 
            Source: Kusche et al. 2016
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the project can be found on the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://belmont-sealevel.org&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Profile</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;research-focus&#34;&gt;Research Focus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m working as a post-doc researcher at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.igg.uni-bonn.de&#34;&gt;the Institute for Geodesy and Geoinformation&lt;/a&gt; at the university of Bonn in Germany. Besides &lt;a href=&#34;#teaching&#34;&gt;teaching&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;#EGU&#34;&gt;EGU&lt;/a&gt; activities, I use space geodesy to study terrestrial hydrology, oceanographic signals and ice sheet changes. I&amp;rsquo;ve (and am) working a lot with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://grace.jpl.nasa.gov/mission/grace/&#34;&gt;Gravity Recovery and Climate Experiment&lt;/a&gt; to study time variable gravity changes. Furthermore, using radar altimetry over the ocean to study sea level changes is another focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my research, I like to think of the Earth as a wobbly substance (a post on that theme is in the making). Many of the signals I&amp;rsquo;m interested in involve the movement of masses (mostly water) just above or below the surface of the Earth. These masses cause the Earth to wobble as they deform the surface of the Earth, change its center of gravity and shift the rotational axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;whereabouts&#34;&gt;Whereabouts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m born and raised in the Netherlands in the city of The Hague and am inofficially classified as a  &amp;lsquo;Hagenees&amp;rsquo;. One can roughly divide the area of The Hague in a &amp;lsquo;high and snobby&amp;rsquo; part and a &amp;lsquo;low and poor&amp;rsquo; part. The more expensive property can be found on former sand dunes, while the more affordable housing is situated in the lower lying areas (read: mud). People living in the former part are commonly known as &amp;lsquo;Hagenaars&amp;rsquo; while those from the latter part are called &amp;lsquo;Hagenezen&amp;rsquo;.

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/The_Hague.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The Hague can be roughly divided into a lower and higher part.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.floodmap.net&#34;&gt; 
            Source: floodmap.net
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only during the final stages of my study of Aerospace Engineering at Delft university of Technology that I became interested in Earth sciences. Although the link between aerospace engineering and Earth sciences may not be obvious at first sight, it may help to think of the mental associative chain: airplanes -&amp;gt; rockets -&amp;gt; satellites -&amp;gt; instruments -&amp;gt; earth observation -&amp;gt; earth sciences. After my study I moved to Potsdam in Germany, to work at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gfz-potsdam.de&#34;&gt;Helmholtz-Zentrum Potsdam Deutsches GeoForschungsZentrum GFZ&lt;/a&gt;. Since 2011, I&amp;rsquo;v been living in Bonn and work at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.igg.uni-bonn.de&#34;&gt;Institute of Geodesy and Geoinformation&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Bonn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;professional-experience-and-education&#34;&gt;Professional Experience and Education&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/DoktorHut.jpg&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The decoration on the &amp;#34;Doktor Hut&amp;#34; pretty much covers where I come from and what I&amp;#39;ve being researching the last years&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014-present, Post-doctoral Researcher at Bonn University, Institute of Geodesy and Geoinformation (chair of Astronomical, Physical and Mathematical Geodesy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007-2014, PhD (Dr.-ing.), in Geodesy, Institute of Geodesy and Geinformation, university of Bonn, The overall theme of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/data/rietbroekPhdThesis2014.pdf&#34;&gt;thesis&lt;/a&gt; covered the combination of several geodetic techniques at once to study for example sea level and Earth deformation effects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2014, Researcher at Bonn University, Institute of Geodesy and Geoinformation (chair of Astronomical, Physical and Mathematical Geodesy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007,2009, Researcher at Section 1.3 Gravity Field and Gravimetry at Helmholtz Centre Deutsches GeoForschungsZentrum (GFZ)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005-2007, Master of Sciences, Aerospace engineering, Delft University of Technology, The Netherlands. In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/data/ae_rietbroek_2007.pdf&#34;&gt;thesis&lt;/a&gt; I compared data from in situ deep ocean bottom pressure recorders with time series from GRACE gravity fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feb-May 2006, Study of Ocean Bottom Pressure Records in the Indian Ocean (Internship) at Ifremer, Brest, France&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2000-2005, Bachelor of Sciences, Aerospace engineering, Delft University of Technology, The Netherlands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-name-egu-a-european-geosciences-union-activities&#34;&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;EGU&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; European Geosciences Union Activities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.egu.eu/g/home/&#34;&gt;Geodesy division of the European Geoscience union&lt;/a&gt; is also something I&amp;rsquo;m involved in. Since 2014, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.egu.eu/geolog/2016/02/10/geotalk-roelof-rietbroek-early-career-scientist-representative/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m fullfilling the role as the early career scientists (ECS) representative for the geodesy division&lt;/a&gt;, and I occasionally post on its &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.egu.eu/divisions/g/&#34;&gt;division blog&lt;/a&gt;. From 2017, I&amp;rsquo;ll follow up &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.egu.eu/ecs/representatives/&#34;&gt;Lena Noack&lt;/a&gt; as the Union Level ECS Representative of the EGU, so this means we&amp;rsquo;re looking for an ECS to represent the geodesy division from 2017 and onward. Interested scientists are invited to contact me by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/r_rietje&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ecs-g@egu.eu?subject=I want to be the next Geodesy ECS-rep!&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-name-teaching-a-teaching&#34;&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;teaching&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Teaching&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/phdcomicsStudent.gif&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://phdcomics.com/comics/archive.php?comicid=1873&#34;&gt; 
            Source: phdcomics.com
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

There are several courses I teach/taught and practicals I supervise. Most of them are in German, which is not my native tongue and occasionally causes some confusion but most of all amusement. To return the favour, I also try to get our German students out of their comfort zones by lecturing in English now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gug.uni-bonn.de/studierende/modulbeschreibungen/20161/291_modulbeschreibung_b24_ggd_20161_160324.pdf&#34;&gt;Globale Geodynamik (Bsc)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gug.uni-bonn.de/studierende/modulbeschreibungen/20152/291-modulbeschreibung-b37-20152-151006.pdf&#34;&gt;Astronomisch-physikalische und mathematische Geodäsie I &amp;amp; II (Bsc)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.igg.uni-bonn.de/apmg/index.php?id=diskretemathe00&#34;&gt;Spezielle Verfahren der Satellitengeodäsie (Msc)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gug.uni-bonn.de/studierende/modulbeschreibungen/20161/340-modulbeschreibung-m28-sgsb-2016-160330.pdf&#34;&gt;Masterprojekt Bonn Space Geodesy Simulator (Msc)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.igg.uni-bonn.de/apmg/index.php?id=537&#34;&gt;Erdsystemforschung mit Satellitenverfahren (Msc)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gug.uni-bonn.de/studierende/modulbeschreibungen/20152/340-modulbeschreibung-m21-20152-150916.pdf&#34;&gt;Globales Geomonitoring (Msc)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;projects-project&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/project&#34;&gt;Projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/project/bandaid&#34;&gt;Band-Aid&lt;/a&gt;: Bangladesh Delta: Assessment of the Causes of Sea-level Rise Hazards and Integrated Development of Predictive Modeling Towards Mitigation and Adaptation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CONTIM: Consistent Ocean Mass Time Series from LEO Potential Field Missions  &lt;a href=&#34;http://gepris.dfg.de/gepris/projekt/273514821&#34;&gt;description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JIGOG: Surface mass redistribution from joint inversion of GPS site displacements, ocean bottom pressure models and GRACE global gravity models &lt;a href=&#34;http://massentransporte.de/index.php?id=210&#34;&gt;former project site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STREMP: Spatial and Temporal Resolution Limits for Regional Mass Transport and Mass Distribution &lt;a href=&#34;http://massentransporte.de/index.php?id=199&#34;&gt;former project site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FIGO: Fingerprints of ice melting in geodetic GRACE and ocean models &lt;a href=&#34;http://massentransporte.de/index.php?id=214&#34;&gt;former project site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>