<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Wobbly Earth</title>
    <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Wobbly Earth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://wobbly.earth/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mind the GRACE Gap, use Swarm</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/mindthegap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/mindthegap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Around Christmas time last year, a falling star, caused by the reentry of the GRACE-2 satellite vehicle, marked the end of an unprecedented gravity mission. It therefore makes sense to find alternatives for the Gravity Recovery and Climate Experiment (GRACE), which can be used to bridge the gap with the GRACE Follow-on mission. A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.solid-earth.net/9/323/2018/se-9-323-2018.html&#34;&gt;recent paper by Christina Lück et al.&lt;/a&gt; now shows whether the Swarm mission can help out in filling this gap.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists! Encrypt your mail if you got nothing to hide</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/gpg_withpforparanoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 20:51:17 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/gpg_withpforparanoid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Up to now, I never bothered to encrypt my email as my attitude was that, as a scientist, I got nothing to hide. But in light of the recently installed science-deprived administration in the US, I&amp;rsquo;m starting to think that a healthy streak of paranoia wouldn&amp;rsquo;t harm after all.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guess what: Sea level does rise when you melt floating ice</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 01:36:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One may suspect that melting of floating ice would not cause a sea level change, but dissolving a chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf may actually change &lt;em&gt;regional&lt;/em&gt; sea level by up to a meter. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your academic homepage: outreach booster or narcissistic outlet?</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-you-really-need-an-academic-homepage&#34;&gt;Do you really need an academic homepage?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the abundance of academic homepages and blogs around, I&amp;rsquo;m certainly not the only one who asked himself that question. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the idea of making one myself for a quite a while now, and finally decided to give it a shot. You&amp;rsquo;re currently looking at the result. For those of you interested in the technical details or the idea behind the domain name, there are posts in the making on that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>