<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Wobbly Earth</title>
    <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Wobbly Earth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 20:51:17 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://wobbly.earth/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists! Encrypt your mail if you got nothing to hide</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/GPG_withPforParanoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 20:51:17 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/GPG_withPforParanoid/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Up to now, I never bothered to encrypt my email as my attitude was that, as a scientist, I got nothing to hide. But in light of the recently installed science-deprived administration in the US, I&amp;rsquo;m starting to think that a healthy streak of paranoia wouldn&amp;rsquo;t harm after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;encrypting-for-the-sake-of-transparency&#34;&gt;Encrypting for the Sake of Transparency?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about lately: Would encrypting email between scientists (and journalists) actually serve the scientific pursuit? Somewhat ironically, will it aid in scientific transparency  by actually preventing censorship and politically motivated interference? I&amp;rsquo;m increasingly inclined to think so, but at the same time, I&amp;rsquo;m ridiculing myself for having these paranoid thoughts and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be the one who&amp;rsquo;s scaremongering. Furthermore, I realize that admitting that you encrypt your email may invigorate conspiracy theories by those who are susceptible. However, under normal circumstances, using an encrypted or unecrypted email wouldn&amp;rsquo;t make any difference at all, and I simply see it as having an additional insurance against unauthorized access.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/snowden-blanket.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Better safe than sorry? Edward Snowden covers himself and laptop while typing his password.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        
            Source: Still from Citizenfour (2014)
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;your-email-may-be-deliberately-taken-out-of-proportions&#34;&gt;Your email may be deliberately taken out of proportions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prime example of emails being deliberately misinterpreted is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climatic_Research_Unit_email_controversy&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Gate Controversy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Where an email server of the Climate Research Unit at the university of East Anglia was hacked in 2009 and more than thousand of &lt;em&gt;unencrypted&lt;/em&gt; emails were stolen. An email where Phil Jones mentions the use of a &amp;ldquo;trick&amp;rdquo; of Michael Mann to &amp;ldquo;hide the decline&amp;rdquo; (in temperature) was exposed in the media as &amp;lsquo;proof&amp;rsquo; that climate scientists were deliberately misleading the public. However, a closer look revealed that it referred to a method to remove a spurious trend in tree-ring temperature reconstruction in favour of more accurate thermometer data, a common and scientifically accepted practice.  And although &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wri.org/blog/2010/07/summarizing-investigations-climate-science&#34;&gt;subsequent investigations cleared the scientists of data manipulation and left the science intact&lt;/a&gt;, these allegations were harmful to (climate) science, and resulted in serious personal threats to the scientists. I can only imagine how frustrating and time consuming it must have been to rebute such claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the amount of emails we send today, it&amp;rsquo;s probably quite easy to find quotes in our inbox which could be falsely interpreted by people lacking context. It therefore seems fair to lock/encrypt your email, to make sure only the recipients get to read them. Sure, if some emails need to be shared for the sake of transparency, one could decide to that on a case by case basis. But letting hackers and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theverge.com/2017/2/12/14583124/nasa-sidd-bikkannavar-detained-cbp-phone-search-trump-travel-ban&#34;&gt;governments frenzy at ones inbox&lt;/a&gt; is outrageous and counterproductive. Failing to encrypt your email, opens the door to unauthorized people nosing through your email, which can have disastrous consequences, ask Hillary Clinton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;staying-ahead-of-the-trump-administration&#34;&gt;Staying ahead of the Trump administration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installment of anti-science cabinet members of the Trump administration and the actions it has taken &lt;a href=&#34;https://arstechnica.com/science/2017/01/have-politics-trumped-science/&#34;&gt;suggest rough times ahead for US and international science&lt;/a&gt;. The possibility of the new administration to censor science in order to push their conflicting policies, seems to become more realistic by the day, and fears that it would hurt the transparency of science don&amp;rsquo;t seem so farfetched anymore. Already, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/powerpost/wp/2016/12/13/energy-dept-rejects-trumps-request-to-name-climate-change-workers-who-remain-worried/&#34;&gt;the new administration attempted to get a list of employees working on climate-related issues at the Department of Energy&lt;/a&gt;. What would they have done with the people on this list? Check their email? Furthermore, the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), essentially responsible for implementing the Paris Climate Agreement, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trump-epa-climatechange-idUSKBN15906G&#34;&gt;was ordered to have its climate section removed from its website&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/climatechange&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; is intended to inform the general public about how climate change has affected and will likely affect the US, and outlines the possibilities for taking actions. The desire of the administration to take out this site essentially sends out the message that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t want the public to be informed about science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So will this administration go as far as to start to monitor the inboxes of scientists? And, on the basis of that information, will they try to prevent scientific research from being published which go against their policies and ramp up gagging orders? I sincerely hope not, but I think it is in the best interest of science to keep ahead and let this administration know of scientific findings &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; being published out in the open. Encrypting your email when you speak to colleagues, journalists and press outlets, is a powerful way to aid this process. Media outlets such as the Guardian are seeing the importance of this and actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/help/2016/sep/19/how-to-contact-the-guardian-securely&#34;&gt;provide guideslines to contact them in safe ways&lt;/a&gt;, but among scientists, encrypting email still seems to be a remote concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;so-how-does-email-encryption-work&#34;&gt;So how does email encryption work?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, when an email program (outlook, thunderbird, etc..) contacts the email server the transport over the internet will be encrypted via a secure protocol (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security&#34;&gt;TLS&lt;/a&gt;). Although most email-servers will drop the security layer when either sender or receiver does not support it, it will work for most modern email-programs and browsers, ensuring that intercepted emails can not be decrypted without disproportionate efforts. Generally however, &lt;em&gt;your inbox will still be stored unencrypted at the email server&lt;/em&gt;, and may therefore be easily read when the server is compromised.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/Orange_blue_public_key_cryptography_en.svg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Use the public key for encrypting and the secret key for decrypting&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        
            Source: Wikimedia commons
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few email providers allow users to store encrypted inboxes on their servers. For example, Protonmail, &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.cern/about/updates/2014/05/cern-inspires-entrepreneurs-email-encryption&#34;&gt;designed by former CERN scientists&lt;/a&gt; offers such services as well as the Berlin based company &lt;a href=&#34;https://posteo.de/en&#34;&gt;posteo&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the time however you can&amp;rsquo;t choose your email provider for work related emailing, which means that you can&amp;rsquo;t control how your inbox is stored on its servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, you can in fact, choose to &lt;strong&gt;store encrypted messages in your unencrypted inbox&lt;/strong&gt;. For this to work, you can use the open source public key cryptography implementation of PGP (Pretty Good Privacy) confusingly abbreviated as GPG &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnupg.org&#34;&gt;(GNU Privacy Guard)&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of this post a few helpful links will be provided in order to allow you to set up email encryption on your devices of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GPG is a so called assymetric encryption implementation. During its setup the user creates a encryption key-pair which contains a public part and a private (or secret) part. The idea is that everybody who&amp;rsquo;s got the public key is able to encrypt a message and send it to you. However, only the owner of the secret key is able to decrypt the message, not even the sender. Mathematically, the principle relies on the theory that it&amp;rsquo;s easy to multiply 2 (very large) prime numbers, but it is computationally very hard to recover those primes if only the product is available. If some genius mathematician would come up with a way to find these primes in considerable less time as expected, it would mean the end of many encryption methods we know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few things to keep in mind about using GPG:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The secret key must be kept stored only on devices one trusts, and must not be handed out to anyone else. Remember, anyone with the secret key can decrypt your messages. Then again, you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to decrypt your messages when you lose your secret key. Note that the entire system breaks down when the end device (laptop, cell phone, etc) is compromised. You commonly store your secret key by encrypting it again with a password, but of course this won&amp;rsquo;t help when a keylogger is installed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To prevent man-in-the-middle attacks, getting someones public key must go over a trusted channel. Otherwise, the man in the middle may sneak in a compromised public key allowing him to decrypt and encrypt the message while on the way to the real recipient. The analog way essentially involves meeting with somebody in person, checking that she/he is actually the person, and then handwrite the key down on a piece of paper. However in practice, one exchanges a fingerprint, which allows a unique lookup of the public key from a trusted key server (that is when the user has decided to store the public key on such a server). It is absolute necessary to have the correct fingerprint, as otherwise you may be getting the wrong &lt;a href=&#34;https://pgp.mit.edu/pks/lookup?search=Edward+Snowden&amp;amp;op=index&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Edward Snowden&amp;rdquo; public key from the server&lt;/a&gt;. To get an idea of how paranoid it can get you may find it interesting to &lt;a href=&#34;https://theintercept.com/2014/10/28/smuggling-snowden-secrets/&#34;&gt;learn how Edward Snowden established contact with the Guardian journalists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tweeting your fingerprint is actually not such a bad idea either, as it is a relatively secure way of publishing your public key. The reason is that twitter uses secure http by default ensuring that your browser obtains the original tweet (i.e. you browser decrypts the tweet similar to the principle used in GPG), making it quite difficult to alter its content along the way. Below is an embedded tweet where I tweeted my GPG fingerprint. Note that this isn&amp;rsquo;t simply an image of a tweet (which potentially could have been modified by a man in the middle), but it is the javascript in your browser directly pulling the tweet from the twitter servers in a secure way. You can check that you got my actual tweet as the hyperlink on the date should get you to the original tweet (if you happen to land on a fake twitter account, or if it is only a simple image of a tweet, you have a good reason to start panicking)
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Getting somewhat paranoid lately, here&amp;#39;s my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/gpg?src=hash&#34;&gt;#gpg&lt;/a&gt; fingerprint  CB56 8BCC 2F04 2DFE E166  2D9B A7DB DDEA FDE4 D78C&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Roelof Rietbroek (@r_rietje) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/r_rietje/status/826666842944966656&#34;&gt;February 1, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keys which are signed by people you trust are less likely to be fake. Key owners have the possibility to sign each others key as an endorsement (I checked that this person is actually associated with this fingerprint), and upload the collected signatures to the public key servers. Have a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://pgp.mit.edu/pks/lookup?op=vindex&amp;amp;search=0x2C6464AF2A8E4C02&#34;&gt;the signatures on the public key of Richard Stallman&lt;/a&gt; for example. Some people take this so serious that they actually go to key signing parties, where fingerprints of the attendees are manually cross checked and subsequently signed. But for now, I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine scientists having key signing parties at scientific conferences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may not be able to read your messages with web-based email interfaces. Since the messages are stored as gibberish on the server, using the web interface of your email provider will show you, yes gibberish. After all your secret key should  not be stored on that mail server, or on that internet-cafe terminal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-to-set-up-gpg-for-your-devices&#34;&gt;How to set up GPG for your devices&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have guessed, this post is not intended to give you a step by step guide to set up GPG on your device of choice, but more to make you aware of the possibilities, and sadly, the eventual necessity, of encrypting your email. However, I would like to point out a few links which may be consulted for setting things up. Note that there are usually more ways to accomplish this but below are a few common scenarios. They all use an underlying PGP tool with which you can manage your keys. This tool then communicates with your email client of choice out of the box or through a plugin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;using-thunderbird-on-linux-windows-or-mac&#34;&gt;Using thunderbird on linux, windows, or mac&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if you&amp;rsquo;re using thunderbird, there is a nifty plugin fittingly called Enigmail. Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://enigmail.wiki/Quick_start&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;quick start&amp;rsquo; guide in setting this up for various OS&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;. As mentioned before, it essentially consists of setting up GPG tool on your system, generating a key and using the plugin.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/enigmailscreenshot.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Using Enigmail in Thunderbird adds an enigmail menu item with several options to choose from&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h5 id=&#34;using-k-9-mail-with-openkeychain-on-android&#34;&gt;Using K-9 Mail with OpenKeychain on Android&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a good email app called K-9 Mail which supports PGP encrypted messages when OpenKeychain is installed on your android device.   &lt;a href=&#34;https://k9mail.github.io/documentation/security/pgpmime_current.html&#34;&gt;Instructions can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;using-apples-mail-with-gpgtools&#34;&gt;Using Apples Mail with GPGtools&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, I know  lot of scientists like to work on Apple products, so I did some searching for you. It turns out that you &lt;a href=&#34;https://gpgtools.org&#34;&gt;can install a Mac port of GPG called GPGtools&lt;/a&gt;. This is supposed to integrate with Apples mail client &amp;lsquo;Mail&amp;rsquo;. Remarkably, GPGtools actually had to reverse engineer the Apple Mail software, as Apple does not provide official ways to write plugins for it. I leave it up to the reader what to think of this&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;using-iosmail-with-ipgmail&#34;&gt;Using iOSMail with iPGMail&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to own an apple phone too, you may want to try out &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipgmail.com&#34;&gt;iPGMail&lt;/a&gt;, which is supposed to integrate with iOSMail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;gpg-as-a-digital-vaccination-program&#34;&gt;GPG as a digital vaccination program&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final note, it is important to realize is that &lt;strong&gt;if you want to facilitate others to send encrypted mail, you have to offer them your public key&lt;/strong&gt;, even if you consider the risk of being compromised yourself low. If scientists don&amp;rsquo;t bother to generate keys, it will become impossible to send GPG encrypted mails. So here&amp;rsquo;s an anology for you: convincing scientists to creating GPG keys is the digital equivalent of establishing a vaccination program&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guess what: Sea level does rise when you melt floating ice</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 01:36:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/archimedes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One may suspect that melting of floating ice would not cause a sea level change, but dissolving a chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf may actually change &lt;em&gt;regional&lt;/em&gt; sea level by up to a meter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post was actually inspired by an email I received last week:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subject: Remember Arquimedes before being silly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Roelof,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melting of the Artic ice sheets contributes ZERO to the sea level rise, simply because they are afloat, its basic hydrostatic!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic mistake and a shame to see these words coming from the mouth of a TUDelft graduate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XXXXXXXX,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naval Architect&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I decided to ignore the email because of its tone, and obvious &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man&#34;&gt;strawman argument&lt;/a&gt;. But, since &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skepticalscience.com/Sea-level-rise-due-to-floating-ice.html&#34;&gt;the Archimedes argument has an interesting twist to it&lt;/a&gt; when ice melts in sea water, it was actually a good incentive to write a post on it. Furthermore, there are obviously still people today, who willfully or unwillfully, ignore the melting of grounded ice masses, while misinterpreting &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archimedes%27_principle&#34;&gt;Archimedes&amp;rsquo; principle&lt;/a&gt; in terms of volume instead of mass. So, I guess it doesn&amp;rsquo;t harm to reopen this case and use the dangling chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;misinterpreting-archimedes-principle&#34;&gt;Misinterpreting Archimedes&amp;rsquo; Principle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having Archimedes in mind, one is inclined to reason that, when floating ice melts, the volume of sea water which it displaces will be perfectly compensated by the added volume from the melted ice. If this would be the case, then no net sea level will result from melting floating ice. However, Archimedes&amp;rsquo; principle itself is formulated in terms of forces which are linked to weight (or equivalently mass) and not to volume:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any object, wholly or partially immersed in a fluid, is buoyed up by a force equal to the weight of the fluid displaced by the object&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will see that, in the case of melting ice in sea water, it certainly is not correct to assume a constant density throughout the melting process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;grounded-versus-floating-ice&#34;&gt;Grounded versus Floating Ice&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/Grounding-line.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A large part of the world&amp;#39;s ice sheets are resting on the bedrock, compared to floating ice which either comes from the calving of glaciers or is formed at the surface during cold winter times.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.antarcticglaciers.org/glaciers-and-climate/ice-ocean-interactions/grounding-lines/&#34;&gt; 
            Source: antarcticglaciers.org
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To get an idea of all the factors at play here, one has to distinguish between ice which rests on the bedrock and ice which is afloat. The other issue, as discussed in this post, is that floating ice may induce regional changes in sea level when melted. I addressed these issues in the email reply, which I repeat here for completeness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear XXXXXXX,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;seeing that you took the effort to write me an email, and noticing that the topic obviously got you emotionally involved, I took the liberty to write you a quick response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to set the record straight, you can not have heard me claiming that floating sea ice is driving  sea level change, so I don&amp;rsquo;t understand where you got that idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, grounded (not floating) glaciers and ice sheets do contribute to sea level change. Besides the obvious Greenland ice sheet, the Arctic houses several islands which are home to grounded glaciers (e.g. Nova Zembla, Svalbard. etc), you only need to have a look at google earth to spot a few of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, and here&amp;rsquo;s some food for thought, melting sea-ice may actually cause (small) changes in sea level.  The salt concentration in ice bergs and sea -ice is less  than that of the sea water which holds it buoyant. So if sea-ice melts in the water , the local salt concentration, and hence the sea water density, decreases. To maintain a constant pressure at the bottom of the ocean, which is a fine assumption when considering the surrounding waters to be unchanged,  one would (regionally) need a higher column of less dense water. The Archimedes argument breaks down there because the density of the water obviously does not remain constant throughout the melting process.  Density changes also occur when the temperature of the sea water changes due to the latent heat needed to convert ice to water, essentially counteracting (some of) the above effect. So regionally, melting of icebergs and sea-ice could in fact cause some sea level change. However, this effect is expected to be smaller than the direct contributions of the grounded ice sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You being a naval architect and former university employee, I trust you to be skeptical enough to reconsider your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kind regards,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roelof Rietbroek&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. In the future, please refrain from using patronizing language such as &amp;ldquo;Remember Arquimedes before being silly&amp;rdquo;, it does not impress me and it degrades an open discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retropect, I apologize for the final sneer, a little patronizing by itself, but considering how the correspondence started of, it could have been worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I won&amp;rsquo;t go into detail on these grounded ice sheets, but these are indeed significant contributors to global sea level rise. It is the floating ice, which either has been calved of a glacier (i.e. ice bergs),  or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lAupJzH31tc&#34;&gt;sea ice which may form at the ocean&amp;rsquo;s surface under wintery conditions&lt;/a&gt;, which will be in focus here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;melting-a-piece-of-the-larsen-c-ice-shelf&#34;&gt;Melting a piece of the Larsen C ice shelf&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time now, scientist have been looking at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projectmidas.org/blog/a-growing-rift-in-larsen-c/&#34;&gt;a growing crack in the Larsen C ice shelf&lt;/a&gt;. The part which could potentially break off covers about 6000 km^2, which is about 1/7th of the Netherlands (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.volkskrant.nl/wetenschap/gigantische-ijsvlakte-antarctica-staat-op-breken~a3851188/&#34;&gt;the area of North and South Holland together&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 9 Jan 2017&lt;/em&gt;: Recently, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/energy-environment/wp/2017/01/06/the-crack-in-this-antarctic-ice-shelf-just-grew-by-11-miles-a-break-could-be-imminent/?utm_term=.ec404d1f60f4&#34;&gt;the crack of the Larsen C has been growing quickly&lt;/a&gt;, and a break up is more likely in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/larsenCchunk.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A crack growing in the Larsen C ice sheet may lead to a significant piece breaking off&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projectmidas.org/blog/a-growing-rift-in-larsen-c&#34;&gt; 
            Source: Project MIDAS
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Using this as an extreme example, one could try to compute the sea surface height change after melting this chunk in a region of the ocean. In order to quantify this in a reasonable amount of time, we would need to make some design choices and simplifications. I implemented these in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/strawpants/IceshelfMeltDemo&#34;&gt;some matlab scripts&lt;/a&gt; which everyone interested can download and tinker with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;1-define-the-chunk-of-ice&#34;&gt;1 Define the Chunk of Ice&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on some educated guesses the following chunk of the Larsen C shelf is to be melted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surface area: 6000 sq. km&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ice Thickness: 200 m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ice density: 917 kg per cubic m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;2-define-the-pool-of-sea-water-to-melt-the-ice-in&#34;&gt;2 Define the pool of sea water to melt the ice in&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the pool of water must be large enough to facilitate the melting of the ice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surface area: 3 times the area of the ice shelf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depth of the affected water: 2000 m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial in situ temperature: (allowed to vary from -2 to 22 deg. Celcius)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial salt concentration: 34.5 &lt;a href=&#34;http://salinometry.com/pss-78/&#34;&gt;practical salinity units&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mean density of seawater: 1027 kg per cubic m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;3-make-a-monster-slush-puppy-from-the-larsen-c-chunk&#34;&gt;3  Make a monster slush Puppy from the Larsen C chunk&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I mean by this is that we conceptually disintegrate the ice shelf and distribute the ice evenly without melting. This step is needed as we want to let the melting affect the sea water evenly over the entire pool of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;4-compute-the-new-temperature-and-salinity-of-the-sea-water-after-melting&#34;&gt;4 Compute the new temperature and salinity of the sea water after melting&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea water and ice are really awkard substances, and respond non-linearly to temperature and salinity changes. To maintain thermodynamic consistency (i.e. conserve energy), I used software from the empirically determined &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.teos-10.org&#34;&gt;Thermodynamic Equation Of Seawater (TEOS)&lt;/a&gt; to compute the sea water response (i.e. new temperature and salinity) to melting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;5-integrate-the-density-changes-over-the-affected-column-to-compute-sea-surface-height-change&#34;&gt;5 Integrate the density changes over the affected column to compute sea surface height change&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the TEOS software again, we can now compute the density from the temperature and salinity profile before and after the melt event. These can than be numericaly intergrated over the entire water column to compute the sea surface height change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melting-the-larsen-c-chunk-of-ice-may-yield-over-1-meter-of-regional-sea-level&#34;&gt;Melting the Larsen C chunk of ice  may yield over 1 meter of regional sea level&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the result surprised me as well. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting sea level changes over a meter. But then again, it is a gigantic piece of ice which has been melted here in a &amp;lsquo;relatively&amp;rsquo; small area. The interesting thing is that the sea surface height change strongly depends on the initial temperature of the sea water. The plot below shows the dependency on the initial temperature of the sea water. And there are some interesting observations which can be made.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://wobbly.earth/images/LarsenCSealevel.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Regional sea level change (blue dashed line) when a 6000 sqkm floating chunk of the Larsen C ice shelf would be melted in a pool of sea water which is about 33 times the mass of the ice shelf itself. The blue area indicates the range of initial temperatures which didn&amp;#39;t allow a complete melting of the ice. The green line indicates the drop in temperature of the sea water.&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Melting ice in colder waters cause a larger sea level rise. The maximum sea surface change (130 cm) occurs close to the point where the melting brings the sea water closest to its freezing temperature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you would tug the ice shelf to tropical waters (&amp;gt; 18 deg. C), the melting would actually cause a sea level drop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The temperature drop of the sea water increases when starting of with warmer waters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, although floating ice is not expected to directly contribute much to global mean sea level rise, it&amp;rsquo;s contribution to regional sea level may be large enough to be detectable with sea surface height measurements such as those from for example radar altimetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that, even for global mean sea level rise, the volumetric changes due to melting of ice shelfs do cause a small net sea level rise. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2010GL042496/full&#34;&gt;Shepherd et al. 2010&lt;/a&gt; found a net contribution of  49 ± 8 microns per year, which is small compared to the currently observed global mean sea level rate of about 3 mm/yr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above experiment comes with it&amp;rsquo;s assumptions (e.g. no circulation and energy exchange with the surrounding waters), but can nevertheless be used as a conceptual model. Readers who find errors in the code are of course encouraged to report this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your academic homepage: outreach booster or narcissistic outlet?</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-you-really-need-an-academic-homepage&#34;&gt;Do you really need an academic homepage?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the abundance of academic homepages and blogs around, I&amp;rsquo;m certainly not the only one who asked himself that question. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the idea of making one myself for a quite a while now, and finally decided to give it a shot. You&amp;rsquo;re currently looking at the result. For those of you interested in the technical details or the idea behind the domain name, there are posts in the making on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best response I got when discussing the starting of blog with friends was probably in the line of &amp;ldquo;Good on you!: but don&amp;rsquo;t you think a homepage is a tad archaic?&amp;ldquo;. Well &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.igg.uni-bonn.de/apmg/index.php?id=rietbroek&#34;&gt;my institutional homepage&lt;/a&gt; sure has a pretty archaic look, and, frustatingly, I can&amp;rsquo;t change that. Interestingly, that&amp;rsquo;s also my prime reason to venture into this: &amp;ldquo;having the freedom to design and style your own public appearance, and being able to better manage your own outreach efforts. Of course one could try to reach out using a facebook profile, but frankly speaking, I don&amp;rsquo;t want facebook to take control over my homepage, and bombard you with irrelevant information (i.e. adds), although I&amp;rsquo;ll certainly use it to share links to reach a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #f0f0f0&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #007020; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; ( Outreach &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; Publications )
{
    &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;Publications;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the current academic situation, outreach efforts are still underappreciated compared to publishing papers, so the incentive clearly lies at publishing more papers instead of building a blog. Most of the research grants I&amp;rsquo;ve seen put the weight (=resources) on researching and publishing in respectable journals, compared to outreach activities (if specified at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that people don&amp;rsquo;t want researchers to reach out to the general public. Recently, Sander Dekker, dutch secretary of the ministery of education, culture and research, plead that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scienceguide.nl/201609/de-echte-waarde-van-wetenschap.aspx&#34;&gt;researchers have the moral duty to communicate their findings to the general public&lt;/a&gt;, but sadly failed to acknowledge that researchers are expected to do this voluntarily in their own (precious) time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have the feeling though that there is a paradigm shift going on. For example, Rolf Hut voiced this in stating that &lt;a href=&#34;http://rolfhut.nl/2016/07/27/why-scientists-should-write-blogs-instead-of-articles/&#34;&gt;scientists should write blogs instead of articles&lt;/a&gt;. I sure won&amp;rsquo;t refrain from writing papers, but it is food for thought, and one&amp;rsquo;s results surely would reach a broader audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also other signs that outreach efforts are getting more important. I personally really like the outreach efforts of the EU funded &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.egsiem.eu&#34;&gt;EGSIEM project&lt;/a&gt;. The website offers regular blogposts on the project&amp;rsquo;s activities, where I should mention that it is a remarkable achievement to gather so many blogposts from fellow scientists, who are busy writing papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Germany, the science funding body &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dfg.de&#34;&gt;DFG&lt;/a&gt; is putting effort in setting an example. Since january 2016, they have their own &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dfg_public&#34;&gt;twitter account&lt;/a&gt; (woop woop!). And since june 2016, they started making &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dfg.de/klimataucher&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; of climate related research targeted at a broader german public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-if-your-homepage-turns-into-a-narcissistic-outlet&#34;&gt;What if your homepage turns into a narcissistic outlet?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely, I hope that the occasional visitor of this website is entertained and informed, instead of being bored by a polished profile of an apparent &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.nl/citations?user=qGuYgMsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;academic research superstar&lt;/a&gt;. That being said, I do intend to show a bit of myself, and to highlight my own research work. And sharing such things should be an enjoyable activity, otherwise it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to start a blog in the first place. Furthermore, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t the researcher himself be the ideal person to disseminate his research to wider public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;double-barrel-science-communication&#34;&gt;Double barrel science communication&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However some may argue that researchers have the tendency to stay too technical (read: boring) when communicating science, and that this task should better be left to journalists. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/life-and-physics/2016/apr/16/justin-trudeau-and-quantum-computers&#34;&gt;Although some journalists think it&amp;rsquo;s even better to have politicians explain the science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4ZBLSjF56S8?&#34; 
  style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with journalistic stories is that they often filter out a fair share of relevant science while shaping the story around dramatic headlines. Honestly, you can&amp;rsquo;t really blame the journalists for doing this, as they &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-wales-34213693&#34;&gt;crucially depend on clicks&lt;/a&gt;, but it may deform the results of the actual study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who said that you have to choose? Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s better to go for a double barrel approach and use both the professional media and a direct piece by the scientist. In such situations, if you have your academic homepage up and running, don&amp;rsquo;t you think it is an ideal place to add those extra bits of science?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>