<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Wobbly Earth</title>
    <link>http://wobbly.earth/tags/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Wobbly Earth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://wobbly.earth/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Your academic homepage: outreach booster or narcissistic outlet?</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-you-really-need-an-academic-homepage&#34;&gt;Do you really need an academic homepage?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the abundance of academic homepages and blogs around, I&amp;rsquo;m certainly not the only one who asked himself that question. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the idea of making one myself for a quite a while now, and finally decided to give it a shot. You&amp;rsquo;re currently looking at the result. For those of you interested in the technical details or the idea behind the domain name, there are posts in the making on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best response I got when discussing the starting of blog with friends was probably in the line of &amp;ldquo;Good on you!: but don&amp;rsquo;t you think a homepage is a tad archaic?&amp;ldquo;. Well &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.igg.uni-bonn.de/apmg/index.php?id=rietbroek&#34;&gt;my institutional homepage&lt;/a&gt; sure has a pretty archaic look, and, frustatingly, I can&amp;rsquo;t change that. Interestingly, that&amp;rsquo;s also my prime reason to venture into this: &amp;ldquo;having the freedom to design and style your own public appearance, and being able to better manage your own outreach efforts. Of course one could try to reach out using a facebook profile, but frankly speaking, I don&amp;rsquo;t want facebook to take control over my homepage, and bombard you with irrelevant information (i.e. adds), although I&amp;rsquo;ll certainly use it to share links to reach a wider audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #f0f0f0&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #007020; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; ( Outreach &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; Publications )
{
    &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;Publications;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the current academic situation, outreach efforts are still underappreciated compared to publishing papers, so the incentive clearly lies at publishing more papers instead of building a blog. Most of the research grants I&amp;rsquo;ve seen put the weight (=resources) on researching and publishing in respectable journals, compared to outreach activities (if specified at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that people don&amp;rsquo;t want researchers to reach out to the general public. Recently, Sander Dekker, dutch secretary of the ministery of education, culture and research, plead that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scienceguide.nl/201609/de-echte-waarde-van-wetenschap.aspx&#34;&gt;researchers have the moral duty to communicate their findings to the general public&lt;/a&gt;, but sadly failed to acknowledge that researchers are expected to do this voluntarily in their own (precious) time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have the feeling though that there is a paradigm shift going on. For example, Rolf Hut voiced this in stating that &lt;a href=&#34;http://rolfhut.nl/2016/07/27/why-scientists-should-write-blogs-instead-of-articles/&#34;&gt;scientists should write blogs instead of articles&lt;/a&gt;. I sure won&amp;rsquo;t refrain from writing papers, but it is food for thought, and one&amp;rsquo;s results surely would reach a broader audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also other signs that outreach efforts are getting more important. I personally really like the outreach efforts of the EU funded &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.egsiem.eu&#34;&gt;EGSIEM project&lt;/a&gt;. The website offers regular blogposts on the project&amp;rsquo;s activities, where I should mention that it is a remarkable achievement to gather so many blogposts from fellow scientists, who are busy writing papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Germany, the science funding body &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dfg.de&#34;&gt;DFG&lt;/a&gt; is putting effort in setting an example. Since january 2016, they have their own &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dfg_public&#34;&gt;twitter account&lt;/a&gt; (woop woop!). And since june 2016, they started making &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dfg.de/klimataucher&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; of climate related research targeted at a broader german public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-if-your-homepage-turns-into-a-narcissistic-outlet&#34;&gt;What if your homepage turns into a narcissistic outlet?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely, I hope that the occasional visitor of this website is entertained and informed, instead of being bored by a polished profile of an apparent &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.nl/citations?user=qGuYgMsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;academic research superstar&lt;/a&gt;. That being said, I do intend to show a bit of myself, and to highlight my own research work. And sharing such things should be an enjoyable activity, otherwise it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to start a blog in the first place. Furthermore, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t the researcher himself be the ideal person to disseminate his research to wider public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;double-barrel-science-communication&#34;&gt;Double barrel science communication&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However some may argue that researchers have the tendency to stay too technical (read: boring) when communicating science, and that this task should better be left to journalists. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/life-and-physics/2016/apr/16/justin-trudeau-and-quantum-computers&#34;&gt;Although some journalists think it&amp;rsquo;s even better to have politicians explain the science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4ZBLSjF56S8?&#34; 
  style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with journalistic stories is that they often filter out a fair share of relevant science while shaping the story around dramatic headlines. Honestly, you can&amp;rsquo;t really blame the journalists for doing this, as they &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-wales-34213693&#34;&gt;crucially depend on clicks&lt;/a&gt;, but it may deform the results of the actual study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who said that you have to choose? Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s better to go for a double barrel approach and use both the professional media and a direct piece by the scientist. In such situations, if you have your academic homepage up and running, don&amp;rsquo;t you think it is an ideal place to add those extra bits of science?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>