<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Wobbly Earth</title>
    <link>http://wobbly.earth/categories/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Wobbly Earth</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://wobbly.earth/categories/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Consistent Ocean Mass Time Series from LEO Potential Field Missions (CONTIM)</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/project/contim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/project/contim/</guid>
      <description>The DFG funded project CONTIM (Consistent Ocean Mass Time Series from LEO Potential Field Missions), is part of the Priority Program Dynamic Earth, and started in 2015 (initially for 3 years). It&amp;rsquo;s primary goal is to estimate and study ocean mass variations using numerical ocean modelling, precise orbit determination of low earth orbiters (LEO&amp;rsquo;s), and data combination approaches. The project is expected to yield results which are highly relevant for closing the sea level budget, indirectly providing constraints on the ocean warming and the related energy budget of the Earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BanD-AID</title>
      <link>http://wobbly.earth/project/bandaid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wobbly.earth/project/bandaid/</guid>
      <description>Bringing together several research disciplines to study the Bangladesh delta The Bangladesh delta is home to over 150 million people and located at the confluence of the Ganges, Brahmaputra and Meghna Rivers. The high population density and flat topography make the delta vulnerable to sea level rise, and storm surges. For example, Cyclone Sidr in 2007 caused over 3400 deaths and an economic loss of about US$ 1.7 billion.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>